let's see two proofs of the Pythagorean
theorem inspired by
uid imagine that we have a right
triangle with legs of length A and B and
a hypotenuse of length C we can draw a
square off the leg of length a and this
Square encloses an area of a * a or a
squ similarly we can draw a square off
the leg of length B enclosing an area of
b^ s we can also draw a square off the
hypoten
and this has an area of c^ 2 in the
picture diagram the Shaded area is a 2 +
b^ 2 ID realized that we can Shear
squares and we maintain the same area we
can also rotate shapes to maintain area
so if we Shear both squares along the
opposite leg of the triangle rotate 90°
and then Shear again down this vertical
line where they meet we end up filling
the C by C Square Off the hypotenuse
this means that A2 + B2 = c^2 where A
and B are the legs of a right triangle
with hypotenuse C this is essentially
ID's proof of the Pythagorean
theorem the shearing and rotation proof
also suggests a dissection proof of the
Pythagorean theorem we can cut the B by
b square like this so that the
Triangular region matches the original
right triangle we can rotate this shape
down and then use the triangle to cut
this region into two shapes dropping
down this top pictured triangle here we
can also cut the a by a square like this
dropping this blue region down into the
original triangle and using the line
shown here to cut another little piece
to fill the last little triangular
region here we rotate 90° and use the
original triangle to create a new small
triangle that then drops down into place
in the C by C Square from this
dissection proof we see that a^2 + b^2
equal c^2 by cutting and moving pieces
around
let's see the original shearing and
rotating proof one more time where we
shear and rotate both rectangles
together you tell me do you like the
shearing and rotating proof better or do
you prefer the dissection that it
implies either way it's nice to have
multiple proofs of one fact and it's
amazing that ukids proof produces the
dissection proof as
well